in the last video I showed that instead
of rotating a 3D Vector with a 3X3
rotation Matrix we can instead rotate it
using a double-sided transformation we
rewrite the vector as a two by two
Matrix called a Paulie vector and
multiply it on either side with an su2
Matrix on the left and the hermitian
conjugate of that su2 Matrix on the
right
some viewers pointed out this looks
similar to rotating vectors with
quaternions which also involves a
double-sided transformation with a unit
quaternion Q on the left and that
quaternion's conjugate Q star on the
right
these look even more similar if we
rewrite the su2 matrices using half
angle trig functions and the sigma
matrices and rewrites the quaternion Q
using half angle trig functions and ijk
it turns out that the unit quaternions
are mathematically equivalent to su2
matrices and in this video I'm going to
show how
first let's review quaternions hopefully
you know that the imaginary number I is
defined such that I squared equals
negative one this allows us to write
complex numbers of the form a plus b i
where A and B are real coefficients
quaternions are like an extension of the
complex numbers where we have three
imaginary units i j and k Each of which
squares to negative one
we can use these two right quaternions
which have the form a plus bi plus CJ
plus DK where a b c d are all real
coefficients
now with quaternions it's not enough to
know that the imaginary units Square two
minus one we also need to know how they
multiply with each other
the standard multiplication rules are I
times J equals k j times k equals I and
K times I equals J
we can visualize these multiplication
Rules by following the arrows on this
circle
for example if we do I times J we follow
the arrows to get k
if the multiplication goes against the
arrows we get a negative sign for
example J times I equals negative k
this gives us an important property the
quaternion imaginary units are
anti-commutative this means that if we
swap the order of multiplication of any
two different imaginary units we get a
negative sign in front
so I times J equals negative J times I
and so on
we can also summarize the quaternion
multiplication rules using this table
however we can derive this entire table
from just four simple formulas
the first three formulas tell us that I
J and K all square to negative one and
the final formula tells us that I times
J times k equals negative one
all possible multiplications can be
derived from these four rules
for example if we take the last formula
and multiply both sides by K on the
right since K squared equals negative
one we can derive I times J equals k
I should also mention the idea of a
quaternion's conjugate Q star
given some quaternion Q we get the
conjugate Q Star by switching the signs
of the imaginary units i j k
if we multiply Q by Q star we get 16
terms where only the diagonal terms are
non-zero
so we get a squared plus b squared plus
c squared plus D Squared which is the
squared length of the quaternion
we say that Q star over the squared
length of Q is the inverse of Q denoted
Q to the negative one
this is because Q times Q inverse gives
us one
now let's review the sigma matrices and
how they lead to su2 matrices
we already introduced the sigma X Sigma
Y and sigma Z matrices in the last video
the I and the sigma y Matrix is the
complex number I that squares 2 negative
one
we already saw these matrices all square
to the identity Matrix which I'm
denoting with this fancy number one
we also know that they anti-commute with
each other so when we swap the order of
any two different Sigma matrices in a
product we get a negative sign in front
so the sigma matrices look a bit like
the quaternion imaginary units they
anti-commute just like ijk but they
Square to positive one instead of
squaring two negative one
here's the key to linking the sigmas
with i j k a single Sigma Matrix will
Square two plus one but a pair of
different Sigma matrices will Square two
negative one
for example if we take Sigma x times
Sigma Y and square it we get to the
sigma's X Y X Y
if we flip the middle two sigmas we pick
up a negative sign which we can bring
out to the front
we're left with Sigma x squared and
sigma y squared which both go to the
identity Matrix so we end up with the
negative of the identity Matrix
we can use a similar proof to show that
any pair of different sigmas squares to
the negative identity Matrix
it also turns out that these pairs of
Sigma matrices also anti-commute with
one another we can show this just by
swapping the individual sigmas step by
step and we end up with a negative sign
in front
so it seems like the quaternion
imaginary units i j k might somehow be
related to pairs of Sigma matrices and
that's exactly right here's the
correspondence between them
there's an easy way to remember this
the quaternion imaginary I is sort of
like the x-axis and this is matched with
negative Sigma y times Sigma Z which is
sort of like the YZ plane which is
perpendicular to the x-axis
similarly J is like the y-axis
associated with the perpendicular ZX
plane and K is like the z-axis
associated with the X Y plane
to prove this equivalence we need to
establish the fundamental properties of
quaternions that each of i j k Square 2
negative 1 and that I times J times k
equals negative one
we've already shown that these pairs of
Sigma matrices Square to the negative
identity
and the fact that we've added a negative
sign in front doesn't change this result
since negative one squares two plus one
next we need to show the equivalent of I
times J times k equals negative one
if we replace i j k with our negative
Sigma pairs we can multiply all three
negative signs into a single negative
sign out in front
the inner pairs of Sigma Z's and sigma
X's go to one and the remaining pairs of
Sigma y's also goes to one so we get
negative one as desired
so these negative Sigma pairs are
completely mathematically equivalent to
the quaternion imaginary units in
mathematical terms we say they are
isomorphic
so how does this fit into rotating
vectors
when rotating with quaternions we can
write a vector v by replacing the XYZ
basis vectors with i j and k
so we get a quaternion with only pure
imaginary parts and no real part
we rotate V with a double-sided
transformation involving a unit
quaternion Q which is a quaternion with
length one
the real part of Q is cosine Theta over
2 and the imaginary part is sine Theta
over 2 times the axis of rotation
for example if we want to rotate
counterclockwise around the z-axis we
set the axis of rotation to K
for the Q star on the right we take the
quaternions conjugate which means
reversing the signs of the imaginary
units i j k
here's a worked example of rotating the
vector k around the J axis by an angle
Theta using some basic trig identities
we end up with some Vector that lives in
the ik plane rotating from The Starting
k-axis by an angle Theta
you might also see this formula written
with Q on the left and Q inverse on the
right this formula works if Q is not
normalized and has a length not equal to
1.
the denominator for Q inverse forces
both Q's to have length one
if we want to do rotations with the
sigma matrices instead we rewrite a
vector v by replacing the XYZ basis
vectors with Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z
and this gives us our Paoli vector
the double-sided transformation uses a
matrix U which equals cosine Theta over
2 times the identity Matrix minus sine
Theta over 2 times the plane of rotation
for example if we want to rotate in the
YZ plane in the direction taking y to Z
we use Sigma y times Sigma Z
for the Matrix on the right half of the
double-sided transformation we take the
complex conjugate transpose of U also
called the hermitian conjugate of U
denoted with the dagger symbol
since the sigma matrices are hermitian
and equal to their own daggers the
daggered applied to a pair of them just
swaps their order which is the same
thing as introducing a negative sign
so this is just the U Matrix but with
the rotation angle working in the
opposite direction so it's really U
inverse
so the dagger is basically playing the
same role as the quaternion conjugate we
saw earlier so it's really U inverse
Since U dagger equals U inverse we call
you a unitary Matrix
another thing to note is that
multiplying U by an overall phase Factor
e to the I Phi will not change the
rotation results since complex phase
factors will cancel out
as I showed in the last video this
allows us to set the determinant of U to
any complex number of magnitude 1 that
we like
so we set the determinant of U to be
plus one by convention making it a
special unitary Matrix su2
here's an example of rotating the vector
Sigma Z in the ZX plane
the math works out in a similar way to
the example we saw earlier with
quaternions
so the quaternion rotation formula is
written in terms of a rotation axis and
the su2 rotation formula with the sigmas
is written in terms of a rotation plane
but both formulas are equivalent related
by this equivalence
so both unit quaternions and the su2
matrices give us a way of rotating 3D
vectors using double-sided
transformations
these are both describing a more General
concept called a spin group in
particular these are two different ways
of describing spin three the spin group
of three-dimensional space
3 is what we call the double cover of
the rotation group SO3
I mentioned before that we normally
rotate 3D vectors using three by three
matrices called SO3 matrices
for every SO3 Matrix are there are two
quaternions that do the same rotation if
Q is a quaternion that does the same
rotation as R then negative Q will do
the same rotation since the pair of
minus signs will cancel out in the
double-sided transformation
the same reasoning applies to su2
matrices for a given SO3 Matrix R there
are two su-2 matrices plus u and minus U
that will perform the same rotation
so the unit quaternions or equivalently
the su2 matrices are considered the
double cover of SO3 rotation matrices
because there are two members that will
do the same rotation for any given
rotation r
if we want to learn to build the higher
dimensional versions of the quaternions
that do rotations in four five six and
generally n Dimensions we need to learn
how to build the spin and group we'll do
this later in the video series when we
discuss Clifford algebras also called
geometric algebras
in the next video I'll show that we can
factor a Pali Vector into a pair of Pali
Spinners where each one transforms with
a single su2 Matrix
so basically we can think of vectors as
objects that transform with a pair of
quaternions and we can think of spinners
as objects that transform with a single
quaternion